Petersen mss., 1781-1935 LMC 1828
Lilly Library
Petersen mss.
1781-1935
Lilly Library
LMC 1828
6 Folders
The Petersen mss., 1781-1935, is a collection of letters from thirty-nine British writers to various friends and associates.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Scott Petersen, bookseller, assembled this collection of correspondence from 39 prominent 18th-20th century British authors.
Scope and Content Note
The Petersen mss., 1781-1935, is a collection of letters from thirty-nine British writers to various friends and associates. Among the authors present are Christopher Anstey, F. Anstey, Clara Lucas Balfour, Shirley Brooks, Sir Francis Cowley Burnand, Sir Henry Channon, Lady Cynthia Crewe-Milnes Colville, Victoria Cross, Lady Elizabeth Rigby Eastlake, Margaret Scott Gatty (Mrs. Alfred Gatty), Samuel Carter Hall, Theodore Edward Hook; Baron Richard Monckton Milnes Houghton; William Jerdan, Richard Payne Knight, Mark Lemon, Sir Theodore Martin, Friedrich Max Müller; Alfred Harmsworth, Viscount Northcliffe; Caroline Sheridan Norton, Oliver Onions, Francis Turner Palgrave, John William Parker, Edward Hayes Plumptre, Adelaide Anne Procter, James Pycroft, Ernest Raymond, George Barnett Smith; Hallam Tennyson, Baron Tennyson; Henry Thompson, Edward Walford, Mary Augusta Arnold Ward (Mrs. Humphry Ward), and Harrison Weir. The collection is in chronological order except that Mrs. Humphry Ward's letter is in a separate folder accompanied by some printed items about her.
Acquisition Information
Purchase. Scott Petersen. Chicago, IL. 1994.
Anstey, Christopher, 1724-1805; Anstey, F., 1856-1934; Balfour, Clara Lucas, 1808-1878; Brooks, Shirley, 1816-1874; Burnand, F. C. (Francis Cowley), 1836-1917; Channon, Henry, 1898-1958; Cross, Victoria; Eastlake, Elizabeth, 1809-1893; Gatty, Alfred, Mrs., 1809-1873; Hall, S. C. (Samuel Carter), 1800-1889; Hook, Theodore Edward, 1788-1841; Milnes, Richard Monckton, Baron Houghton, 1809-1885; Jerdan, William, 1782-1869; Knight, Richard Payne, 1751-1824; Lemon, Mark, 1809-1870; Martin, Theodore, 1816-1909; Müller, F. Max (Friedrich Max), 1823-1900; Northcliffe, Alfred Harmsworth, Viscount, 1865-1922; Norton, Caroline Sheridan, 1808-1877; Onions, Oliver, 1873-1961; Palgrave, Francis Turner, 1824-1897; Parker, John William, 1792-1870; Plumptre, E. H. (Edward Hayes), 1821-1891; Procter, Adelaide Anne, 1825-1864; Pycroft, James, 1813-1895; Raymond, Ernest, 1888-1974; Smith, George Barnett, 1841-1909; Tennyson, Hallam Tennyson, Baron, 1852-1928; Thompson, Henry, 1797-1878; Walford, Edward, 1823-1897; Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920; Weir, Harrison, 1824-1906
- 1781-1849 (Short 1, Folder 1)
  - Thompson, Henry, 1797-1878. To William Elliott Oliver, 1838, January 10 (Short 1, Folder 1)
  - Pycroft, James, 1813-1895. To Mitford, 1840, November 19 (Short 1, Folder 1)
  - Anstey, Christopher, 1724-1805. To [?], 1781, August 4 (Short 1, Folder 1)
- 1850-1883 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Procter, Adelaide Anne, 1825-1864. [] To Mrs. Hawes, 1850 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Jerdan, William, 1728-1869. To [?], 1853, February 11 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Parker, John William, 1792-1870. To [?], 1853, March 4 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Balfour, Clara Lucas, 1808-1878. To Lord Alfred Paddington, 1854, Aug. 23 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooks, Shirley, 1815-1874. [] To Lucas, 1857 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Gatty, Margaret Scott, 1809-1873. To Mr. Brewin, 1866, September 19 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Eastlake, Elizabeth Rigby, Lady, 1809-1893. To Lady Florence Bell, 1870, February 8 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Hall, S.C. (Samuel Carter), 1800-1889. To John Colborne, 1873, Dec. 31 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Weir, Harrison, 1824-1906. To J.J. DuBois, 1877, July 14 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Burnand, F.C. (Francis Cowley), Sir, 1836-1917. To Benington Foote, 1878, September 7 (Short 1, Folder 2)
  - Smith, George Barnett, 1841-1909. To Julia Goddard, 1879, June 2; n.d. (Short 1, Folder 2)
- 1884-1899 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Plumptre, E.H. (Edward Hayes), 1821-1891. To [?], 1884, December 8 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Tennyson, Hallam Tennyson, baron, 1852-1928. To John Haines, 1893, Dec. 4 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Anstey, F., 1856-1934. To Lady Lyell, 1894, Aug. 22 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Müller, F. Max (Friedrich Max), 1823-1900. To [?], 1895, March 19 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Schmalz, Herbert Gustav, 1856-1935. To Miss Sammin, 1899, July 21 (Short 1, Folder 3)
  - Anstey, F., 1856-1934. To Roy Coventry, 1899, October 1 (Short 1, Folder 3)
- 1900-1935 (Short 1, Folder 4)
  - Northcliffe, Alfred Harmsworth, viscount, 1865-1922. To Sladen, 1900, January 1 (Short 1, Folder 4)
  - Onions, Oliver, 1873-1961. To [?], 1913, August 7 (Short 1, Folder 4)
  - Cross, Victoria, 1868-1952. To Mr. Stokes, 1924, September 5 (Short 1, Folder 4)
  - Colville, Cynthia Crewe-Milnes, Lady, 1884-1968. To John Wilson, 1931, October 17 (Short 1, Folder 4)
  - Raymond, Ernest, 1888-1974. To Hannah, 1935, March 17 (Short 1, Folder 4)
- n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Channon, Henry, Sir, 1897-1958. To [?], n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Hook, Theodore Edward, 1788-1841 To [?], n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Houghton, Richard Monckton Milnes, baron, 1809-1885 To Larracliffe, n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Knight, Richard Payne, 1750-1824. To [?], n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Lemon, Mark, 1809-1870. To Bell, n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Martin, Theodore, Sir, 1816-1909. To James Maitland? (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Norton, Caroline Sheridan, 1808-1877. To [Henry] Reeve, n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - ---. To [?], n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Palgrave, Francis Turner, 1824-1897. To Madame Mohl, n.d. (Short 1, Folder 5)
  - Walford, Edward, 1823-1897.. To [Julia] Goddard, n.d. (2) (Short 1, Folder 5)
- Ward, Mrs. Humphrey (Short 1, Folder 6)
  - Ward, Mary Augusta (Arnold), 1851-1920. To T. Cook, 1892, November 18 (Short 1, Folder 6)